Let's take a look at Task 15.
Here we are asked to extend our tree program or
animation from Task 4 into a continuous animation
where the trees change their leaf
color according to the seasons.
So the leaves turn orange and
then the trees lose their leaves.
And also it's not just a single tree, but
the tree from Task 4 should get some friends.
And they all together change the color
of their leaves according to the season.
Okay, so if you've done the CodeWorld tasks up
to this point, this shouldn't be too difficult.
We have some helper functions given here
that let us do the month letterings.
And also a transparent color definition
that we can use to make the leaves go away,
as we'll see shortly.
Okay, for now, I've pasted
the tree from Task 4 in here, and it just does
this short shaking animation like it did in Task 4.
So now you should make this
animation never-ending.
It's easy; we did it with this offset
parameter in our solution for Task 4.
And this depended on the time, whether or not the
tree was doing something or just standing still.
So we just take out the condition and
now the tree always does the movement.
Okay, so then let's maybe add the
lettering indicating which month it is.
We just use the month function.
Let's start by giving it a fixed value.
The month function takes an
integer, basically saying
which month it is, 1 corresponding
to January up to 12 to December.
Straightforward.
Okay, so now the month is shown behind the tree;
that's probably not the best-looking option.
So we translate a bit down.
Missing an "s" there; okay.
So this is all very static now.
How do we get the month to change?
Well, let's define the month
m depending on the time.
If we look at this
example, here it seems like every second the
month is changing, so let's do this too.
How do we do this?
Well, we can floor the time, giving us the
number of seconds that have passed, full seconds.
And then, since we want to get a
value between 1 and 12, we can just
get the rest from the division
by 12 using mod (modulo) 12.
And this gives us a value between 0 and 11.
So we add 1 to it so we get
a value between 1 and 12.
So this will now start in January and go all the
way up to December and then circle back around.
Okay, so now we can use this value m to actually
tell the tree which colors the leaves should have.
So let's just pass this as an additional
parameter to the tree function.
Add the parameter here, and
for the trunk and the branches,
this is not important, but the crown
should receive this information.
So we also add this parameter to the crown,
and now the color needs to
change according to this m value.
Let's define a function leafColor
that takes this Integer and gives us
the color for the respective season.
So leafColor takes some Integer and returns
some Color, and what should that be?
Well, let's start with the options we have.
We have green, orange, and the transparent one.
And it should be green from ...
If you look at our reference
here, from March till July.
So m should be between 3 and 7.
From August to October we have orange;
that means m is between 8 and 10.
And in all other cases, the color of the
leaves is transparent, so they vanish.
Okay, so we start out with no leaves,
switch to green leaves in March,
continue till July, switch to orange leaves,
and then lose the leaves again in November.
Okay, very good.
Straightforward changes, I would say.
Now let's add some additional trees here.
They should have different sizes, so
we use dilated to scale down a bit.
Let's add two trees, like in the reference.
Obviously, we need to place them somewhere,
but, okay, they are behind this big tree now.
Let's translate this one maybe
a bit to the right and slightly up, so
it looks like it's standing further away.
And we're doing the same with the
second tree in the other direction.
Let's see how it looks.
Okay, this is basically what
we have in the reference.
Three trees of different sizes changing the
color of their leaves according to the season.
Okay, there are probably a lot of
other ways to achieve the same effect.
What's important here is that you remember
to share as much of this code as possible.
We are obviously reusing the tree and scaling it
down and moving it around, but we also could have
in theory done all this checking on m, for
example, here with lots of different guards,
and then repeating this right-hand side over
and over again with different color values here.
Making sure to reuse as much code and
duplicate as little as possible is the
key here to obtaining a clean solution.